ALYSSA GOODMAN: So, Rebecca, welcome to PredictionX.
Thank you so much for joining us.
And we usually ask our guests to introduce themselves,
so please go ahead and explain your role and interests.
REBECCA HENDERSON: My name is Rebecca Henderson.
I'm a professor at the Harvard Business School at Harvard University.
Ever since I was 21, I've been obsessed with large companies that cannot seem
to respond to change.
I spent 20 years at MIT, a lot of it as the Eastman Kodak
professor of management.
That was a coincidence, but a deeply ironic one.
Because that's what I studied.
And just about the time Kodak went bankrupt, I moved to Harvard.
And I've been at Harvard for 10 years now.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: No coordination between Kodak going bankrupt?
REBECCA HENDERSON: It's a complete coincidence.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: OK, just checking.
Just checking.
Great.
And so as you know, today I was hoping that you
would serve as our expert or one of our experts
about how business firms use predictions in their short-term and long-term
planning.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So business in general uses predictions
in two kinds of ways.
And I think it's really important to differentiate between them.
One is what we might call in using predictions in business as usual.
So suppose I'm trying to understand how many computers I sell this year
or how many soybeans I can expect to grow.
There will be groups inside every significant firm that's
using state of the art models to try and predict that future.
And in that sense, the future tends to be well defined, fairly narrow,
and fairly short term.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And the models are based on their past experience?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Usually.
I mean, all the talk about big data and so on-- firms
are trying to make these models more sophisticated.
But they're essentially extrapolations of the past.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And this would be what we would today
call data science, the kind of--
REBECCA HENDERSON: Yes.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --process that they're doing.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Exactly.
Exactly.
And then there's another class of models.
And of course, there's a spectrum here.
And in practice, these blend in to each other.
But there's another class of models which
is, how do we predict what might be really different from today?
So a concrete example of that would be the challenge facing the automobile
industry today.
They know that a number of major changes are coming down
the pike towards them, including autonomous vehicles,
the switch to electrification.
And those interact with each other.
And nobody knows the timing.
And those are sort of major strategic predictions about the direction
of the whole market.
And that's really a different thing.
That's very different from the, what is the price of soybeans model going
to be?
And I know much more about the second than I do about the first.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Right.
OK.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So in our time together,
I'd really like to talk about prediction in the context
of these major strategic decisions.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Perfect.
Great.
That would be great.
And so if we want to talk about climate as our prime example to start with,
what sort of the range of-- what kind of companies, or firms,
or what particular examples, if you want to give them,
are thinking the most deeply about medium and long-term plans?
And what strategies do you think don't work in terms of people
aren't thinking about it enough or they're not planning in the right way?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So there's a whole range of people
thinking about climate seriously.
In general, you've got people in the insurance industry
who are thinking about long-term risks and what they can insure.
You're looking at people in the energy industry who are wondering
what kinds of power plants to build.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And these are people who stand to potentially make money
if they get it right.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Or lose money.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Or lose money if they don't.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Mostly, the existing players
are at risk from a major accelerated transition.
Then there's a whole group of new players
who are keen to sell the stuff that will fix climate change.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Things like solar panels.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Solar panels, more efficient buildings,
better water usage.
Because we're going to run low on water.
So there's a whole industry of firms who are thinking,
we have solutions to climate change.
And so they're very concerned with what might happen.
There's the food industry, because climate change
has such enormous implications for the supply chain and food.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And does it matter?
I mean-- because you know there is this distinction between actual climate
change and slowing climate change where something like solar panels
might make a difference and then climate change mitigation,
where you know something like being prepared for water shortages
would make a difference.
And so is there any difference in the approaches to those actual climate
change, versus climate change mitigation strategies, or it's all one?
REBECCA HENDERSON: That's really interesting.
And one of the things I want to talk about is large segments of the business
community continue to act as if climate change isn't really going to happen.
And that's not because they don't think climate change is going to happen.
It's because you have an enormous pull towards business as usual.
I mean, if you're a business person, and you're trying to make payroll,
and you're trying to keep the lights on, you're an entrepreneur,
you're living this, you have to be continually focused on today,
right now, the next three months.
And so thinking about longer time frames and the ideas
that the world might be really different is surprisingly
difficult in an organizational context.
And climate change is difficult for that reason,
because it's happening sometime in the future.
And it's invisible.
And, yes, I read the predictions, but how good are they?
So they're relatively easy to ignore if it's not right in your face.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So that's one issue.
And the reason I bring this up is, yes, there
are firms beginning to think about mitigation.
But far more people are thinking about how
to stop climate change than how to mitigate it,
partly because thinking about mitigation is very emotionally wrenching, right?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It's like we're done for.
We have to just stop the damage.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I mean, we know that a fair amount of warning is locked in.
And so people thinking about heavy infrastructure who are thinking they're
going to build barriers across Boston Harbor.
People are beginning-- design that and think about it.
People in the food industry where you're already seeing droughts and floods.
So a lot of conversation about, how do we maintain the food supply
in the face of these kinds of shifts?
But the big money, until quite recently, has
gone into renewable energy, trying to stop it happening.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And how much progress you think is being made there?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So the prices of renewable energy,
the costs of renewable energy has dropped much faster than anyone
expected I was a technology booster.
I mean, I was at MIT for 20 years.
I spent a lot of time telling people that if we got serious about climate,
that the technology would get better a lot faster than anyone thought.
But it's got better, faster even than that.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: That is good news.
REBECCA HENDERSON: It's really good news.
And in fact, when you're looking to build a new power
plant in many parts of the world now, you
would build renewable before you built fossil,
even without accounting for the health costs of fossil fuels.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And without accounting for subsidies.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And without--
yes, without accounting for subsidies.
Again, it has to be particular areas.
But we're now routinely seeing solar and wind quoted on a per kilowatt hour
basis below fossil fuels.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: One of the things that we're
going to talk about with Dan Kammen is we asked him.
So we have a series called The Undiscovered
at Radcliffe, which is about scientific discoveries that
weren't quite completely surprises, but you're sort of looking for something.
But then you find something kind of unexpected.
And so one of the examples that we use is talking about Malthus and Malthus
saying that the whole world was going to starve.
Because he couldn't possibly-- when calculating the food
supply and the population growth in making a forecast,
couldn't anticipate nitrogen fertilizer.
And so the nitrogen fertilizer comes along.
And suddenly, the food supply is completely changed.
And so one of the questions we want to ask
Dan, who's thought about these kind of things sometimes, is,
is there some technology out there that has the potential
to be the nitrogen fertilizer for climate?
And so in the businesses you've talked to about this,
does anybody think that they have some kind of solution like that?
Or is it just that all of them might go just--
or many of them would go a little bit faster and a little bit faster?
Or is there going to be some magic thing that no one thought of?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So I ask engineers and scientists in this area
all the time.
And no one thinks there's some amazing discontinuity.
The most obvious candidate would be fusion power.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And there are venture capitalists continuing
to fund investment in fusion.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I was an undergraduate 30-something years ago.
And in my hall monitor was working on fusion power a MIT.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So I know a venture capitalist
who's part of a consortium that's put over $800 million into a fusion plant.
I mean, he really thinks this time it's going to happen.
I think-- I mean, let's hope it does.
I think the odds are low.
I do think there's a broader phenomenon there which your question gets out,
which I call techno fantacism.
A lot of people I know refuse to think about climate change,
because they assume if it's--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Some miracle.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --really bad, something will happen.
Human beings are intensely creative and productive.
We'll come up with something.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: We'll go to Mars.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And they don't understand the feedback
effects inherent in climate change.
And they don't understand the stock flow problem.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Let's talk about that a little bit,
about these feedback effects and prediction.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well, so these are two separate things, right?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: But I meant in the modeling.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, in the feedback effects?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yeah, yeah.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Right.
Well, you'll want a scientist in here.
But I know enough to be dangerous.
The issue with climate change that makes it really tricky
is there may be discontinuities caused by feedback effects.
So the most obvious is the frozen methane in the northern tundra.
So there's an enormous amount of methane buried in the northern tundra
if the climate heats up--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Under the permafrost?
REBECCA HENDERSON: --under the permafrost.
There's a lot of methane buried under the permafrost
and also, under the sea in so-called methane clathrates.
And if the climate heats up sufficiently to unfreeze this methane,
it will be like a huge shot of greenhouse gases
into the environment in ways that will kind of do
a massive increase in warming.
And once you've got the massive increase in warming,
then you get other kinds of feedback effects coming in,
like the ice might start melting faster.
And so, yes, maybe we'll lose Greenland and the Antarctic ice shelf
faster than we had anticipated.
And then these become reinforcing feedbacks.
And humans are terrible at internal models of effects.
And it's very interesting.
Can I show you one of the tools I use--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yeah.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --to try and get business people to think about--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Please.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --discontinuities--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Sure.
Show us.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --and how the future might be different from the past?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Definitely.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So this is a very simple technique
derived from the work of Peter Schwartz who
was working at the Shell Oil Company.
And he was trying to get the people in the company to think about the fact
that the price of oil might be very different tomorrow
than it had been historically.
And most of us on a day-to-day basis assume that the future
will be pretty much like the past.
So what you do with this technique is you pull a bunch of managers
into the room.
And you ask them, tell me, what is it you're really worried about?
What is it that you mostly suppress, because you don't want to think about
and could really change your business?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Involving what would happen in the future?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Right.
So for example, if you're an energy company,
might there be real global carbon regulation or even
strong local carbon regulation?
Or if you're an energy company, how quickly
will the price of renewables fall?
Or if you're a food company, will consumers really
care about whether you're growing climate-friendly organic food or not?
So these major, major uncertainties.
And the first time I did this, I was doing it about the future of MIT
as an educational institution.
We covered the entire wall with major uncertainties.
We didn't want to think about it.
And that typically is what happens when you do this.
So then you take each uncertainty.
Get the group to choose the two that are most critical.
And the way to get at that is you say, if someone from the future could visit,
like someone from the future is about to walk into this room, what
are the two questions that you really want to know the answer to that
make a big difference--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: In events.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --to the future of your business?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Right.
Great.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So if you're a car company,
do we have autonomous vehicles?
Did that work out?
And electric vehicles-- did we fix the storage problem?
Has the grid electrified and when?
So those would be the obvious questions.
You then take those questions.
And you draw a two by two matrix.
Now, I appreciate you're talking to a lot
of very sophisticated experts in this.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I like two by two matrixes.
This is good.
REBECCA HENDERSON: But this is a way of just really communicating
big groups of people very clearly.
So let's take, for example, are we going to get carbon regulation in the future?
So we say no carbon regulation.
And then we have yes, carbon regulation.
And then let's have renewable energy, is really just a niche.
The costs never go down far enough.
And we never really fixed the distributional problems.
And we still have a base load power problem.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Not broadly adopted.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Not broadly adopted.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Got it.
OK.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And this is renewable energy is cheap and easy, OK?
And you have to be clear what frame you're asking.
So you say, OK, I want you to imagine it's 10 years from now.
And what do you think this is?
And you get the group itself to generate the odds.
You don't go out and get experts.
What you could do--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: You just say--
REBECCA HENDERSON: But you say--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --what do they think?
REBECCA HENDERSON: --what do you think?
What do you really believe are the odds here?
And I did this analysis with a whole bunch of energy companies
five, six years ago.
And you would typically get no carbon regulation.
That's what's going to happen.
All this talk about carbon regulation-- not in my lifetime.
It's some greenie plot.
And then renewable energy is going to be cheap and easy.
It's like, give me a break.
Maybe in whenever.
But if you ask people five years ago, they were like, ha,
I don't really think so.
And so you get people to generate their own odds.
And one of the things about these odds, which is nearly always the case,
is that they are more skewed than the general public.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Toward the business as usual.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Yes.
So when I show my students this, they're like, you're kidding.
They really thought this was the future?
But the thing is you have to work with the psychological biases [INAUDIBLE]..
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
Exactly.
We've covered that a lot in talking about predictions.
REBECCA HENDERSON: OK, so this is exactly the same dynamic.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And what's going on with this two
by two, as you will immediately see, is that this is business as usual.
This is go away, don't bother me.
We're going to succeed forever.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Which is the 70/70.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And that is 49% odds.
And this, which we might call green paradise--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It's 9%.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --is 9%.
So there's a couple of really interesting things about this.
One.
Is this sort of green paradise with these odds
is indeed a low probability event.
And that's the psychological thing that's going on in people's heads,
is there's not going to be a green paradise.
Go away and stop bothering me.
But the other thing that's going on here is business as usual is less than 50%.
And if you can get a group of business executives to see this and internalize
this on uncertainties they chose themselves--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Then they have to accept change.
REBECCA HENDERSON: ----[INAUDIBLE] chose themselves.
Then they go, oh.
And so I sometimes think of my whole research career
as about, how do you make the idea that the future might
be different from the past?
Really salient in everyday practice.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Well, part of it--
I think because people want to know what that future is.
It's like the person coming through the door and telling you the answers,
right?
REBECCA HENDERSON: And they want to know the specific future.
And what this tool does is begin to go-- to open up
where we could have cheap renewables, but not carbon regulation.
What would that be like?
We might have carbon regulation, but expensive renewables.
So it really kind of makes it easier to think about the future in more
complicated, narrative ways.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And you mentioned that there
are some socially responsible investors who
are really interested in asking the leaders of these firms
to say, what is your plan under these scenarios?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Absolutely.
And this is the interesting part is you can make predictions.
And you can have some cool person come in and give you the science.
But getting the organization to act on it requires,
OK, let's have a team that focuses on, is this going to happen?
And let's learn more about it.
And so you've got a group of socially responsible investors walking
into these large fossil fuel companies, food companies, construction
companies, insurance companies and saying,
OK, the science is pretty clear.
The world is heating up.
How is your business going to change?
And they're trying to trigger exactly this kind of moment,
which is to get the organization to sit down and pay attention to it.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And not to get too much into politics.
But does it matter whether the people at these firms,
who have to make the decisions about the direction of the company,
believe that it's human caused climate change, or that it's not?
Because obviously, if it's human caused, we
can maybe do something more about stopping it than if it's not.
And so that should figure into their strategy.
And so I'm just curious whether the kind of political mood
changes the way people make these predictions.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So I talk mostly to larger corporations.
I have not met a single person from a large corporation
who doesn't believe that climate change is real and human caused.
Everybody knows it's happening.
The question is getting anybody to act on it.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: That's right.
Well, some of it--
I mean, what I see--
and even-- I'll just say a very short little story.
There's somebody.
I hope he's still with us.
His name is Arthur Kleinman.
And he used to be a professor at the-- or he still
is at the medical school in the anthropology department.
And he wrote a book about despair.
And he gave a talk once that I went to.
And one of the examples he gave was a psychological condition
where people are rationally afraid of everything, which
would make them unable to go outside.
So if you read every newspaper article and you said your toothpaste
could be contaminated.
You could get hit by a car when you stepped into the street.
You could get skin cancer from the sun, on and on and on.
And he said that what humans need in order to go on
is an appropriate level of denial, that you actually
have to tell yourself that some of these things aren't going to happen to you.
And statistically, that's true.
Not everything is going to happen to you.
But if you took the worst case scenario of everything,
you would just not go outside.
And so I see that some people when they think about climate change are just--
they just think we're, screwed.
What are we going to do anyway?
I'll just keep living and live it up my last days.
And they don't think about their grandchildren.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well, no.
And you get a form of death anxiety and despair,
particularly because people feel they have no agency, right?
There's nothing they can do, so why think about it?
But that's at the individual level.
The large companies-- so one of the things that really puzzles me about
climate change in business is why we haven't historically seen a stronger
movement among the heads of the world's largest corporations to insist
on climate regulation and to insist on a price for carbon or a tax--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: A global climate--
REBECCA HENDERSON: --for carbon.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --regulation?
REBECCA HENDERSON: A global climate regulation.
Because if your business collectively-- so here's the issue.
Collectively, business clearly has a strong economic case
for acting to prevent or ameliorate climate change.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Of course.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Because it's not good for business in the long term.
The trouble is you'd say, well, it's a collective case, right?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And the problem is if one person does it, then
the other person-- yes, exactly.
REBECCA HENDERSON: You can put solar panels on your roof,
but I'm not going to bother.
Because you're the one that's paying to drive the technology down the learning
curve.
I'm just going to wait until it's cheap, and then I'll move.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: There's a name for that in game theory.
I'm trying to remember what it is.
REBECCA HENDERSON: It's the free rider problem.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It's the free rider problem.
REBECCA HENDERSON: This is a huge temptation to free ride.
So you have to somehow coordinate everyone in moving.
And that sounds kind of difficult. But it turns out
that a thousand firms are roughly--
depends on how you measure it--
70% of the world's GDP.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: So if they agreed.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So could you imagine that 300 CEOs?
And we know a hundred.
There's a project sponsored by some investors called the Global Climate
100, which is targeting the 100 largest emitters.
If you could get them to move, you'd make a huge difference
on the whole platform.
So there's a really interesting issue here about the individual firm
responding to predictions and then the business community
as a whole looking at this prediction.
I haven't met anyone who doesn't think it's going to be an issue
and trying to trigger that kind of collective action.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And what about tapping into their employees own values
and their employees own opinions about all of this?
What do they do there?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well, so there's a really interesting question here, which
is even individual firm's response to climate change
and the way they think about using these predictions
shaped by their values or their perception of their employees' values.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And the answer to that is absolutely yes.
And I think there are three kinds of firms we might want to talk about.
There's the firm where the CEO believes that climate change is
an existential threat to the future of the planet
and probably to the future of his or her business.
And it turns out that those are the firms that took the risk to move first.
So Walmart, for example, had for many years more solar panels
installed than any other entity in the United States.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Walmart-- which is associated
with a lot of red America [INAUDIBLE].
REBECCA HENDERSON: Exactly.
No, because they looked at what was happening.
They wanted to make a difference.
They could do the long-term economics.
They could see it made sense.
Or Paul Polman at Unilever, who could see what climate change was
going to do to the food supply and to the lives of the most
vulnerable people.
And so he made-- started making very serious investments early on.
And that was driven by--
and it's this-- in the context of business,
it's always really interesting.
Because you can't just impose your moral vision on a company.
That wouldn't be at all appropriate.
But every business decision is shot through with uncertainty.
Do I take this prediction seriously?
What kind of rating do I give it?
What kind of weighting do I give it?
How do I think about the future?
Those people who are really strongly aware of climate change
because they feel it's a real threat, and that we have a moral responsibility
act, have been much more likely to see the economic opportunities.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Now, I'm not sure this is a fair way
to ask this question, because it's not really, exactly your field.
But in the financial crisis, my people, the physicists,
were blamed for creating the models that the bankers who
were trained more traditionally didn't understand, but went ahead and applied.
Because they saw that in the short term, they were making money.
And so those physicists and mathematicians, as we both know,
get called quants.
And so somewhere in these companies that you're talking about,
even the very sort of socially responsible ones,
there's a bunch of quants.
Or they bring in people who are making these sophisticated models that we'll
talk about in other parts of PredictionX.
And my question is how much of the leaderships' and the employees'
response to what they think is going to happen with climate change
is guided by modeling that they may not understand.
And how much of it is guided by just a kind of value judgment?
That these people who I think I trust as scientists are saying something
really terrible is going to happen.
And I could do something about it.
So I should do something about it.
And so I guess part of the motivation for all of PredictionX
is to get people to understand how models of climate change are made
and how uncertainty is calculated, associated with them,
and even, as I showed you earlier, uncertainty with the weather forecast.
And how much uncertainty is there?
And we can make predictions.
We're not sure.
That doesn't mean it's not going to happen.
And so my question is kind of, how important is it
to both the leaders and the people who are working
to make this happen at other levels, to understand
the quantitative modeling of the climate,
as opposed to just that people they might trust or hopefully trust
are telling them something terrible is going to happen?
And just to go back to what I was saying,
the banking situation was that the bankers wanted to trust the quants.
Because they were telling them, you could make money if you did this.
And the short run, they weren't making money if they did that.
But now, if you trust the sort of climate equivalent of quants,
they're saying disaster looms if you do nothing.
And they don't want to hear that information.
And so is the response different to those kind of predictions
than they were to the financial prediction?
REBECCA HENDERSON: It's really interesting.
I hadn't thought about it this way.
But I think we could, at a very high level,
divide the way business use models into two phases.
In the early phase, it was some people I trust say something really bad
is going to happen.
And I can do something about it at no cost to myself.
So it turned out that saving energy, reducing energy usage,
and gradually moving into renewables was not more
expensive than doing business as usual.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: So why not?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So why not?
And the sort of, I trust what people say and it's going to be really bad,
was so bad that you didn't need to know exactly how bad it was
going to be in order to start moving.
So that's the first phase.
The second phase is people are beginning to get
to the edge of what they can do--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Costlessly.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --without having to spend extra money.
So that gets really interesting.
Now, you really want to know, how much do I need to do?
And remember, you've got to be sure that everyone else is going to do it, too.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: That's this collective.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Because we're solving the collective action problem, right?
If I'm the only person who invests in renewables,
because it's the right thing to do, and I drive up my costs
and my competitors do not, I look stupid and possibly out of a job.
So what's happening now is that the firms are turning increasingly
to the scientists.
And they're saying give me what's called a science-based target.
I need to know how fast you want me to bring my emissions down in order for us
to avoid dangerous warming.
And that's really having an effect on the conversation.
And that means you really need a good model.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Right.
And the problem is that that also has to have
a model of what all the other firms are going to do
and what governments are going to do.
REBECCA HENDERSON: That's a second order thing.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: No?
Really?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Just know for the moment.
What is my allowed carbon emission allowance?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: But how do you know that if you don't know
what everybody else is going to do?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Because that's only a question about the physical system.
That's not a question about the economic system.
So the question is, if we have to limit to 1 and 1/2 degrees of warming,
what does the world's emissions have to be?
And at what rate do they need to slow?
And therefore, I will slow emissions--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Oh.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --at that rate.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: But that does make an implicit assumption
that almost everybody slows at that rate.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well, I wouldn't call it an implicit assumption.
I would call it a strategic hope--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: OK, that's better.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --which you hope will be
enforced by your employees and your customers and please your governments.
And the sense that nobody else is going to move
or not nearly as fast as we'd like.
So these leading edge firms are taking the predictions.
And they're saying, this is what a science-based target is.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I see.
So let me just make sure I understand what you're saying.
So let's say that I'm a company.
And my level of emissions in some units is 10.
And then the prediction is that if we reduced that level-- if everybody
reduced their level emissions to 8, we would limit the climate
change to 1 and 1/2 degrees.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Exactly.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: So I'm going to take my emissions that are 10
and make it 8 and hope that mostly everybody else is.
But I don't have to make it 3.
And if I make it 9.99, that's not going to help.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Exactly.
And in practice, what's happening-- and again,
I'm generalizing horribly-- is businesses
are coalescing around serious reductions to zero by 2050.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Zero carbon emissions?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Zero carbon emissions by 2050.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: From energy usage?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Right.
And of course, the shape of that slope really matters, right?
So there's a lot of conversation about what that slope should be.
But that's sort of how the conversation is increasingly structured around
[INAUDIBLE].
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Do you talk to companies through the branches of companies
or companies that are based in the developing
world where this is a harder problem?
REBECCA HENDERSON: That's a really great question.
So this problem is both harder and easier in the developing world.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: They don't have so much business as usual infrastructure?
REBECCA HENDERSON: They don't have so much business as usual infrastructure.
And in fact, you can see the effects of climate change much more easily.
So if you're in Bangladesh, or you're in the Philippines, or you're in India,
you can see these effects.
And in fact, one of the energy companies I know that is the most--
was the most aggressive was a company based in Hong Kong,
a company called CLP.
And they were based in Hong Kong.
And they were the largest energy provider to Hong Kong,
but they had great hopes of branching out and serving other markets.
And they agreed as early as 10 years ago to make serious investments
in renewables.
I mean, they were way ahead of the curve,
because they wanted to become the expert in that area.
And they thought a lot of new capacity would
be brought-- built out in that area.
Now, on the other hand, as you would guess,
I mean, you do have-- we have no money.
It's not our fault. But if you look at where the serious investments were
made in solar energy to drive down the cost curves, that was in China.
Why?
Because China is nearly large enough to internalize the climate
change externality.
Sorry.
That was too jargony.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I got it.
But you say it again.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Yeah, climate change is sufficiently big,
that they can see that even if they have to pay most of the cost of averting it,
it's worth averting.
Because it's going to have such enormous effect--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: An effect upon them.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --on China.
I mean, the Tibetan Plateau.
Glaciers are melting.
I mean, there's just horrible effects, and they can see it.
So paradoxically, you've got some of the most aggressive actions against climate
change going on in the developing world.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It reminds me, actually, a little bit
of the situation with cell phones and credit cards,
where they don't have so much of an infrastructure.
And they wind up having more modern technology.
REBECCA HENDERSON: But we have to be really careful.
Because I believe China is still building a coal plant a week.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: A coal plant a week?
REBECCA HENDERSON: That certainly was the rate until quite recently.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Wow.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Because coal is so cheap.
And it's so easy.
And the center doesn't control the periphery in China.
So you have local governments with strong incentives
to put on line really dirty, cheap energy.
And in India, it's a similar dynamic.
I mean, India should be all solar.
And they're trying, but it's very problematic at the moment.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Do they buy solar panels from China?
REBECCA HENDERSON: That's a great question.
I don't know the answer.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I don't know either.
But that's interesting.
Because it's like whether your local industry has an impact
and whether there's international perspective.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well, one of the things China was doing
was trying to give their local industry an advantage in these new technologies.
And they succeeded in doing that.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Right.
And now, we have people resisting buying Chinese solar panels in this country.
So this actually brings us to a slightly different question, which is not,
again, quite up your alley.
But I'm curious to know what you're thinking
if you want to talk a little bit about the interactions between all
the different things that you have to predict,
if you wanted to make a proper model of the world's response to climate change.
REBECCA HENDERSON: To climate change?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Right.
You've thought about this.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I have thought about it.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: We know no one can actually do this.
And that you're not necessarily an expert.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And this is not my special field.
But of course, I think a lot about this.
So first, you would need a physical model
of how the physical system is going to respond as we ramp up carbon emissions
or cut them.
Second, you need a model of the effect of changes
in temperature on the Earth's system.
What will be the effect on agriculture?
What will be the effect on sea level rise?
Then you need a model of--
several models.
One model is, will people move to avert these things?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Or when will they?
REBECCA HENDERSON: And if so, when?
And how fast will they move?
And nobody knows.
My belief is if we decided we wanted to do something,
we would move much faster and further than anyone expects.
I mean, I tell people when I'm really depressed about the future,
I pick up economic histories of World War II.
Because they show what humans can do when they're really motivated.
I mean, the Russians moved their entire industrial infrastructure more than a
thousand miles east in like--
tell me how quickly they did it, like really fast.
So I think we would respond much faster, but that's a huge uncertainty.
And we don't know how much money they would put into it.
We don't know how fast the technology will change.
I mean, maybe there'll be a--
we can take carbon out of the air for free
and break the second law of thermodynamics, maybe.
So that's a big uncertainty.
And then there's huge uncertainty about when the effects of climate
start to hit.
How will that affect the planetary political system?
Because there's a whole bunch of risks we haven't talked about,
but could interact with climate change.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Wars over water, for example.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Wars over water, accelerating probability of pandemics,
all kinds of mass migration.
The Department of Defense is most worried about mass migration following
climate change.
There's a report just--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Across international borders--
REBECCA HENDERSON: Across international.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --especially quick.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I mean, there's a report that was just out this week
suggesting that within 30 years, we'll see migration at a scale that
makes current day migration look tiny.
And will that happen?
And how will the world respond?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And of course, if you plan for it in advance,
it would be different.
And you're going through these things in a systematic way,
because you're just listing them.
And you're saying then, then, then.
But we both know that the truth is that they all
interact with each other in real time.
REBECCA HENDERSON: They all interact with each other all the time, right?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Right.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And we don't know how to predict that at all
and which is why--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: We should still try.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, we should absolutely still try.
But I think one of the important things that the models--
so I'm sure you talk about this a lot in the course.
But effective prediction and motivating behavior
is not giving you a point estimate, like the future will be X.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: No.
REBECCA HENDERSON: It's giving you a sense of the shape of the distribution.
Because one of the issues about climate change is
there are these awful tail events.
One of my colleagues estimated some significant fraction--
15%.
Civilization ends as we know it.
And how do we communicate that?
And communicate it in a scientific way or in a way that's intuitive?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Especially if you want to avoid this kind of fatalism problem
where the minute people hear there's a 15% chance even that civilization ends.
They just think, I should have a party.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well-- and so one of the things
we should talk more about in this debate is
I published a book called Accelerating Innovation In Energy Lessons
From Multiple Sectors.
And it was looking at how innovation had been much, much faster
in a whole range of sectors than anyone had ever expected.
And sort of giving a sense of when prediction
is wrong in the positive direction and how that might really
help us with climate change.
But that doesn't mean we sit around and do nothing.
That means we invest to try and find these ways of responding.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: That's right.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Yeah.
And I mean, there are incredibly interesting entrepreneurial firms who
are really trying to find the technologies that
will make a difference in water, and energy, and sea level rise.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And are any of those firms making money already?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So the firms in water--
it turns out a lot of our water infrastructure
is really inefficiently managed.
And so new water saving technologies.
That's a huge and rapidly growing market.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And I imagine something having to do with the power grid
would be similar.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I was going to go to renewables.
So manage the utilities more efficiently, really
put in place distributed generation.
I mean, there's a lot of money--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ALYSSA GOODMAN: So even if you came up with, say,
a software project that would change the power generation strategy.
And then you--
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, there are lots--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: [INAUDIBLE].
REBECCA HENDERSON: --of those.
Right.
Lots of people investing in that way.
Lots of people trying to invest in load balancing, in energy use reduction.
We use energy incredibly inefficiently, because it's basically
been priced for free.
So there's a lot of money to be made in this space.
The trouble is you'd love to know, what is the time horizon for when consumers
will be willing to make these kinds of investments
and when regulators will start to be really excited about these issues?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Where do you get-- and again, this is not necessarily
a fair question for you, but I'm just curious.
So I've had experiences where somebody holds
a particular opinion, whether about health, about politics, about anything.
And the only way to change their mind is if something happens either
to them personally or somebody in their family that completely shows them
that they were wrong, something that they thought wasn't real is real.
Or something that they thought was real isn't real, et cetera.
And so are there stories you've seen of kind of epiphanies
in this way, where a company was sort of living in a kind of denial world
and then something happened where they sort of woke up and went,
oh, wait a minute.
I do have to pay attention to this.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So can I assume you're
talking to a bunch of people about these kinds of errors?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: OK, so I don't need to talk about that.
But concrete examples.
So let me give you a couple.
My favorite is a phone call I got about five years ago from a CEO I know well.
And he said, Rebecca, you know I think the sustainability,
climate change stuff is basically all bullshit.
And I said, yeah, Fred.
Not his real name.
Fred, I know that.
And he said, you know what?
Everyone I'm trying to hire doesn't think so.
So would you come and talk to us about what's going on,
and how we might think about it, and how we might respond?
And so I know a lot of companies where it was the employees who pushed people
into taking this seriously.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I was wondering if that was the case.
Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I mean, I know one company, a big timber company, which
was pushed into harvesting, making a significant change in their policy
with regard to old growth forests by the fact
that their employees complained that when they went to school meetings,
it was too embarrassing--
PTA meetings.
It was too embarrassing to be working for the company.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Ooh.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And you can see that happening across a range of industries.
So one of the things that can change is the gestalt about,
what is the taken for granted right thing to do?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I mean, no one would say on camera,
I'm going to employ children.
Because let's face it.
That's the way to maximize profits.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Super cheap.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Super cheap.
And they don't give you any trouble, and they never unionize,
and you can chain them to the looms.
I mean, let's do it.
No one is going to say that in public.
And I think it's possible that in fact that
might happen with respect to climate.
Now, there are very complicated political dynamics
around beliefs around climate in the US, not elsewhere [INAUDIBLE]..
ALYSSA GOODMAN: That's where people realize it's real.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Really realize it's real.
And we could talk about the politics if you're curious.
But the other thing that seems to be happening is if you get hit not once,
not twice, but three times by a major--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: By a flood or--
REBECCA HENDERSON: --climate related event.
Then even if you really didn't think it was true, you start to think it's true.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: That's true.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And there's some evidence
that voting behaviors in the Carolinas in this last election
were shaped by the fact that they've been hit three times.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yeah, so tell me more about what
you think about the political situation in the US if you want
and why it's so different than other places.
REBECCA HENDERSON: No, I'd happy to.
So until quite recently, the Republican Party
admitted the scientific reality of climate change.
And in fact, people like Senator McCain advocated for climate legislation,
and it was considered bipartisan.
One of the things that's happened in the US over the last--
depends how you time it, but 30 to 40, 50 years
is the Republican Party, which one might think
of as the party of the establishment and of business
has made common cause with what we might call the old southern party, which
was primarily interested in minimizing the size of the federal government,
largely to involve interference with their racial policies.
And so there was a very effective alliance
where these two parties came together and said,
we want to get rid of government.
We want to scale it down.
The first, because we don't like taxes and regulation.
And the second, because we really don't like the federal government telling us
who we can live next to, or who we have to go to school with,
or who we have to allow access to our elections.
And so that's been an incredibly powerful political alliance.
And what that has sort of cemented is an ideology that government is bad.
Government wants to control you.
And so we have a lot of people thinking that climate change is a conspiracy
to stop you driving your car or doing what you want with your land.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Although I still don't understand why.
Why would the government want to have that conspiracy?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, because that's what governments.
Governments want to control your--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Stop you from things.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --life.
Government wants you to stop you from doing things.
And so let's get rid of government.
Government is them.
Government is the elites.
Government is remote.
And as we know, to an unfortunate degree,
government has been elite, remote, and not
doing the right thing for people on the ground.
So it's played into this ideology.
And so now we have a lot of people who cannot be persuaded that climate change
is a real possibility, even if you bring them people who speak their language
and share their faith traditions.
It's very, very difficult to [INAUDIBLE]..
ALYSSA GOODMAN: But if unfortunately, they experienced three floods in a row,
[INAUDIBLE].
REBECCA HENDERSON: Now, If they've experienced three floods in a row, now
we're beginning to get change.
And of course, this varies by demographic.
And it's this sort of really focused denial lists
are a relatively small share of the population.
And that number is moving.
And I'm sure you're showing people the Pew statistics.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I think also there's a difference that's
important between denialists and there's no word for it, like ignoralists.
Or--
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, I love the ignorness.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --I just don't pay attention.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I just don't pay attention.
I don't think about politics.
Maybe there's climate change.
No, no.
And that's an important segment.
But it is true now that if you ask, a majority of the US population
believes that climate change is real and that we should act against it.
And there's more and more people wanting to put it higher
up their list of priorities.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yeah, [INAUDIBLE].
REBECCA HENDERSON: So one of the reasons I think business action in this area
is really important is I think there's an interaction between employees
want me to focus on climate.
So I'm going to focus on climate.
And, oh, every big company focuses on climate, and says it's real,
and put solar panels on their roof.
Maybe it's really happening.
So I think there's an effect of the private sector on--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Have demonstrated.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Yes, a demonstrating effect, a legitimization effect.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: So is it really true that the price of real estate in Miami
hasn't fallen, even in response to their total acknowledgment of climate change,
and the changing coastline, and floods?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So one particularly interesting example
of the complete disjunction between my cognitive
understanding that climate change is happening and action in the world
is the price of Miami real estate, which really should have fallen by now.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: You'd think.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I mean, we have persistent flooding,
saltwater incursions.
And yet, if you go to the beach in Miami--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I see building buildings on higher and higher stilts
and charging more and more.
REBECCA HENDERSON: They are building the buildings up a bit.
But the skyline is a mass of cranes.
And that whole area is going to be under water in 30 years, 50 years.
I mean, really, really soon.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: What a world.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And I heard a fantastic interview
with on NPR with a Miami real estate agent who said, yeah,
we know climate change is happening.
No, I'm buying and selling condos in this area,
because we're going to sell them in three or four years.
And there'll be someone who wants to buy this great condo.
And so you've got a classic--
I mean, some of my colleagues call it a carbon bubble, which
is we know there's a carbon bubble.
We know there's going to be a massive
ALYSSA GOODMAN: [INAUDIBLE]
REBECCA HENDERSON: --reallocation of asset prices at some stage.
But everyone's like, oh, but not this year.
And of course, if you're using an 8% discount rate,
anything more than six or eight years away is infinitely distant.
And so because we think the world is going
to be more or less the same, which is where we get the discount rate,
then we don't make investments that would allow us to ensure that.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: In the long term.
REBECCA HENDERSON: In the long term.
Right.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Wow.
OK.
Well, so if we talk about totally life changing technologies,
one thing that we could talk about is artificial intelligence,
robotics, machine learning, the changing nature of work.
And so how do you think that impacts the future when
it comes to climate and other aspects of people's economic lives?
REBECCA HENDERSON: So that's a really--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Huge question.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --interesting question Yeah.
So what's the interaction between AI robotics and climate?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So let's go positive first.
One of the big impacts of climate change that's becoming increasing clear
is to make it very hard to work outdoors in certain regions of the world.
And so the ability to automate agricultural work
and to use much less water, much more fertilizer,
to really sort of upgrade agriculture is going
to be absolutely central to human well being.
And so the combination of AI big data and then robots--
you could imagine that really making a huge--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --stop a lot of health problems.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Exactly.
So as in nearly every industry, there's a kind of light side of AI robotics,
which is really exciting.
I think the potential dark side is that we don't manage the transition.
So I think in the long term, it's clear AI robotics will be what economists
call a general purpose technology, like electricity, or computing, or the steam
engine.
And it will dramatically increase the productivity of the economy
and bring us all kinds of benefits.
But there'll be, wait, transition costs?
And transition costs of things like the major accounting firms
are planning to--
stepped on the hiring by 25%, 50%, 75% over the near future,
because these new technologies allow them not to hire.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Employers.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And the major accounting firms are the largest--
my understanding is they're the largest hire
of white collar people out of college.
Or let's just talk autonomous driving.
I'm sure you've seen the predictions of the millions of people who
are likely to be thrown out of work.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Now, you can things in the long term,
this is a stupid way for human beings to spend their time.
And the AI will make sure that the transportation network is much cleaner,
much more efficient, that the vehicles are allocated much more effectively.
So from a carbon point of view, we would love
AI to run the transportation systems.
From a human point of view, what are we going to do with the 1 million,
2 million, pick your number people who are thrown out of work?
And they may in turn, contribute to very significant political unrest.
And if we get significant political unrest, which
makes us focused increasingly on the short term and on populist solutions
to our problems, we will not respond effectively
to the challenge of climate change.
And it will degrade our political capability.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: So what do we think about things like a guaranteed minimum
income?
Is that realistic?
In other words, where you take people?
And we know that the Industrial Revolution
made the workweek much shorter.
And do you get to the point where people just work less, and you retrain people,
or some people don't work at all?
Or there's other things people do with their time?
Do people think about this?
REBECCA HENDERSON: Absolutely.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Discuss this?
REBECCA HENDERSON: There's a lot of discussion in this area.
I'm not a super special expert in this area,
but I know enough to be dangerous.
So it's clear that we have to think about this problem.
Amongst the solutions are significant increase in education, thinking
seriously about how you make AI and robotics a complement
to human skills and not a substitute.
And that's an innovation project.
And so a lot of firms are beginning to think about,
how do you bring in the new technology, so it up skills everyone and makes
us all more productive, rather than just automating what we have.
So that's a big issue.
Investment in health, because that just makes everybody possible.
And then the minimum income-- there will be some people who cannot transition
or are incapable of working.
And I myself believe it's very important to support them.
I'm nervous about a guaranteed minimum income.
Because I believe work is one of the great sources of human self-respect--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I think so, too.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --and of creativity and flourishing.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And of stopping you from being bored.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Absolutely.
Plus, a guaranteed minimum income is unbelievably expensive.
I would much rather put the money into--
let's kick up demand for education and health.
Let's use that to drive the expansion of the economy to generate services we
really need.
Now, this is a very live issue amongst economists.
And nobody knows the answer.
I suspect we'll need a mix of everything.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: I just have one weird thing to tell you
about the autonomous vehicles scenario.
I don't think I've told you, but I recently acquired Tesla.
And it does drive itself.
And the thing that's really weird is that the kind of human machine
partnership that it is now is this form of self-driving car
where you have to help it.
So you can make it keep driving in a lane on a road.
You can even tell it to change lanes, and it'll
find the right place to change lanes.
But it does not take you from point A to point B.
REBECCA HENDERSON: It could.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It understands.
But it could and it doesn't.
And so I understand--
I just learned yesterday that Apple and Google are apparently holding out
for the world where you're at point A and you want to go to point B.
And it frees the human from kind of worrying about the act of driving,
whereas right now, you're in this weird place where it's a human computer
partnership, where it's almost another skill to kind of control the computer,
rather than to drive the car.
It's very bizarre until you've experienced it.
But it's sort of-- if you're driving down a road where there's not
self-driving cars and people who--
yesterday I was behind somebody in the tunnel under the Science Center
at Harvard.
And they were going 15 miles an hour in this tunnel,
whereas you know people go 30, 40 miles an hour.
And I said to the passenger I was with--
you think they're texting or lost?
And as a human, you have some expectation about,
there's something wrong with this person.
And I don't want to go too near that car.
But the self-driving car doesn't understand that.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, interesting.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: OK, so the danger to this human computer partnership
is mixing pure human with human computer partnership.
Because the computer doesn't yet understand.
And so you talk about all these transitions.
But there's this weird transition.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Right.
And there's going to be a bunch of these kind of transitions.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
And so I'm sort of trying to think of other examples.
And it wasn't until I actually owned this car that I went, oh, my God.
This is so weird.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Well, you could imagine.
This is not my field, but you can imagine similar ambiguity
in the medical arena, where the AI--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
REBECCA HENDERSON: --can help you diagnose.
And how much reliance you put on the diagnostic?
And it could go either way.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And the doctor won't take seriously
the machine predictions, which are even now statistically better
than most doctors, or too seriously, and it depends.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Exactly.
So it seems like there's this whole--
we've been talking about people's attitudes, and people's relationship
with quants, and everything.
And I think the kind of education that may be needed--
and we talked about this with Ben Schneiderman,
actually, in terms of algorithmic accountability,
is getting people to a point where they least understand
what these algorithms are trying to do if they're
going to live in this hybrid world where they're
cooperating with these algorithms.
REBECCA HENDERSON: But this is exactly what
I mean when I say we have to make these technologies a complement
to human skills.
Because there's a persistent fantasy that I
think has haunted my business for at least the last hundred
years, which is if we found the perfect machine, we can get rid of the humans.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Well, in some cases, yes.
I mean, think about an elevator, right?
An elevator in a building-- that's why I always used that as the dumb analogy
to a self-driving car.
An elevator used to have an elevator operator.
They had to stop at exactly the right floor.
They talked to you.
It was very chatty, very nice.
I barely remember this from when I was a little baby.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Yeah, I remember that.
Yeah.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: OK, but that doesn't exist anymore.
And now, there aren't even buttons on elevators in some very fancy buildings,
because there's some algorithm that's allocating the elevator.
And you have to tell it where you want to go in advance
and this creeps people out.
REBECCA HENDERSON: But so there are some tasks we definitely want
to automate and get the humans out.
But there are other tasks.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Where we don't.
REBECCA HENDERSON: I mean, there's a huge literature about,
for example, if you want to order a loan for me, should I trust the software?
But we're beginning to see the software encodes all kinds of racial and gender
biases.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes, yes.
We talked about that with Ben, too.
Yes, yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And how do we think about that?
And how should business think about?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yeah.
And so I think it's not just a problem for academics.
I think it's kind of like how you had to retrain the workforce
to use electrical power tools, right?
I think you have to retrain the workforce to understand--
REBECCA HENDERSON: That's happening now.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --these problems.
REBECCA HENDERSON: We had to retrain everyone
to think about statistical process control and continuous improvement.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Not everyone, but some people.
Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: But a lot of people, many more people
than you usually expect.
And what are the tools of continuous improvement?
And how do we think about this not as a static process,
but as an evolving process?
ALYSSA GOODMAN: But I have to tell you that one of the things
that I was really surprised about in terms of this effort, PredictionX,
we were really trying to get to people who
might not have thought about climate change simulation and how it was done.
And there's a certain preaching to the choir.
And I hope that if this does make it to the video,
that people are not already in the choir.
But there is this issue where it's really hard
to get to the people who don't want to think about this stuff.
And when you mix in the AI and the robotics,
which are even harder for people to kind of--
REBECCA HENDERSON: But they don't have the same emotional reason
to shut down when you start talking about it.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: No, they have an emotional reason to embrace it.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Exactly.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Because if it's not about their job,
then they're like, awesome.
Great.
I don't have to do that anymore?
Roomba-- that vacuum for me.
Terrific.
And so I think people are accepting of all these things, which got us
to terrible for us food, and inefficient energy networks,
and all this stuff that was just kind of convenient at the time.
And so what I worry about when it comes to AI, and robotics,
and all of this stuff is people not understanding
what they're getting themselves into and not even wanting to think about it.
REBECCA HENDERSON: One of the interesting implications
of AI in particular is the ability to extract patents
from enormous disparate pools of data.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And so one of the things
firms would like to know is, where are you?
How much money you have.
And what would you buy?
And so you can integrate an enormous amount.
You can use facial recognition.
You can use purchases.
You can use cell phones, tracking.
So you could develop the kind of complete surveillance software
that an authoritarian state would like, just for private gain.
And in fact, in this country, at least until quite recently,
it looked as though a large platform companies
would sew up a lot of this crucial data and use it
as a source of money for themselves.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Facebook, for example.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Facebook.
But others, too.
I mean, there's a--
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It's interesting.
Because among the Radcliffe Fellows, we have
a bunch of people who are from former Eastern Bloc countries.
And when they see the kind of stuff that people who are
American mostly put on Facebook and Twitter--
REBECCA HENDERSON: They can't believe it.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: --they can't believe it.
No, they can't believe it.
Because they're just giving away this information.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Right.
Right.
Why would you do that?
Don't you understand you're being watched?
So again, this is not climate change.
But I think there's a way in which business
may be tempted to use these technologies in a way that accelerate
some potentially very negative effects.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Anything that you'd like to end on a happy note?
[LAUGHTER]
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, sure.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Anything else?
You can look at your notes again if you want to.
REBECCA HENDERSON: So sometimes people ask me why I'm optimistic,
given how much I think about climate change and the issues we face.
So there's a couple of reasons I remain not optimistic.
Because I think optimistic implies I'm sure that everything's
going to work out OK.
So I'm going to say hopeful.
So the reason I stay hopeful, but not optimistic is--
there's a couple of things.
First, I really mean it in saying that the technology will
move much faster than we expect.
And we're already beginning to see that.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: There's evidence of that.
Yes.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Secondly, that when I started teaching the course
I teach at the Harvard Business School, which has the tiny title of Reimagining
Capitalism--
Business and the Big Problems, 28 students showed up.
And this year we had nearly 400, which is nearly half
of the second year at the business school.
And so my reading of not everyone, but many people
are deeply concerned about these questions
and really believe that there are issues about the future of the planet
and the health of our society.
And, yes, you could say these are not very precise predictions.
But they are sure that there are high odds something very nasty will happen,
unless we start doing things differently.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And that they see it is so important to help.
Yeah.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And so many of the students
can see business models that will help.
And so they're moving to do things.
Because we are an incredibly creative and ingenious species.
And there's a kind of chicken and egg problem here, right?
If we all thought climate change was real
and we needed to do something about it, we
would create a huge market for the technologies that would avert it.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: It would be space program.
REBECCA HENDERSON: And that would drive down-- everyone down the cost curves.
It would make it much cheaper.
And we would get it done.
And so to me, the whole question is, when is that avalanche going to start?
It is going to start.
And all of us are tiny, but we can all be pebbles in that avalanche.
And at some stage it's going to roll.
And I'm sure it's going to roll.
Now, it won't be quick enough, because that would've been 20 years ago.
But anything we can do is going to be better than doing nothing.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: And from what you were saying before,
you're thinking that that avalanche might even
start in a country that's not ours.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Oh, yes.
Yes, yes.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Yeah, that's interesting.
REBECCA HENDERSON: We tend to think everything starts here.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: No.
REBECCA HENDERSON: Not necessarily.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: Well, [INAUDIBLE] because we're
notorious for being very creative and innovative in this country,
especially with technology.
But this is a case where technology and policy are really
not headed in the same direction.
REBECCA HENDERSON: It's interesting.
Because, by historical standards, America has been really good at seeing
there's a new industry coming, and investing in the R&D,
and triggering the demand.
But in this instance, we've been really a laggard.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: OK.
Well, let's look to the rest of the world.
And I say thank you, thank you, thank you very much.
REBECCA HENDERSON: You're very welcome.
ALYSSA GOODMAN: This was perfect.
Perfect.
REBECCA HENDERSON: My pleasure, really.